<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A faithful warning with good counsel and advice to the rulers &amp; magistrates in England that they not countenance wicked and merciless men to oppress and spoil the innocent under pretence and colour of a  law / by one that really desireth the prosperity of the truth and the welfare of all men, Alexander Lawrence.</title>
            <author>Lawrence, Alexander, d. 1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49753</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L650</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30490</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11342646</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11342646</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47505</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49753)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47505)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1465:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A faithful warning with good counsel and advice to the rulers &amp; magistrates in England that they not countenance wicked and merciless men to oppress and spoil the innocent under pretence and colour of a  law / by one that really desireth the prosperity of the truth and the welfare of all men, Alexander Lawrence.</title>
                  <author>Lawrence, Alexander, d. 1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.l.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47505:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:47505:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
            <p>A FAITHFUL WARNING WITH GOOD COUNSEL &amp; ADVICE, TO THE Rulers &amp; Magiſtrates IN ENGLAND, That they may not <hi>countenance</hi> Wicked and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs Men to oppreſs and ſpoil the Innocent under Pretence and Colour of a Law.</p>
            <p>By one that really deſireth the Proſperity of the Truth, and the Welfare of all Men, <hi>Alexander Lawrence.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>And Judgment is turned away backward, and Juſtice ſtands afar off; for Truth is fallen in the Street, and Equity cannot enter.</p>
               <p>Yea, Truth faileth, and he that departeth from Evil maketh himſelf a Prey; and the Lord ſaw it, and it diſpleaſed him that there was no Judgment, <bibl>Iſa. 59.14, 15.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:47505:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47505:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <head>A FAITHFUL WARNING WITH GOOD Counſel &amp; Advice, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>TO You <hi>Rulers</hi> &amp; <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in this Nation and elſe-where, who think to eſtabliſh Cruelty and Oppreſſion by a Law, and thereby to exalt your ſelves, and Lord it over the Heritage of the moſt High God, as the Seed of Evil-Doers did in all Generations, as you may read in the Scriptures of Truth, <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.2. and ſo on. <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that great Oppreſſor, when <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> ſpake unto him, to let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go to ſerve the Lord, ſaid, <hi>Who is the Lord that I ſhould obey his Voice, to let</hi> Iſrael <hi>go? I know not the Lord, neither will I let</hi> Iſrael <hi>go,</hi> &amp;c. but inſtead thereof made their Task heavier, <hi>v.</hi> 6.7. So proud <hi>Haman</hi> whom King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> gave Command that all ſhould bow unto, but honeſt-hearted <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai,</hi> who was as much or more the King's Friend as <hi>Haman,</hi> did not therein obey the King's Command, knowing <hi>Haman</hi> to be of the <hi>Agagites;</hi> and when <hi>Haman</hi> underſtood, he was vexed, but thought it Scorn to lay his Hand on <hi>Mordecai</hi> alone, but ſought the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all the <hi>Jews,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Eſter</hi> 3. at large. And for <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> who made an Image of Gold, and ſet it up in the Plane of <hi>Dura,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and commanded that all ſhould, <hi>at what Time they heard the Sound of the Cornet, Flute, Harp, Sackbut, &amp;c. fall down and worſhip the Golden Image, &amp;c.</hi> Dan. 3. at large; but <hi>Shadrach, M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhach</hi> and <hi>Abedn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>go,</hi> whoſe Hearts were upright and ſtedfaſt before the Lord, would not; and it was told the King, and the King was full of Fury, &amp;c. and ſaid, <hi>Who is that God that ſhall deliver you out of my Hands,</hi> verſe 15. <hi>&amp;c?</hi> And the back-ſliding <hi>Jews,</hi> when their Hearts turned from God, though they cryed, <hi>The Temple of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. yet they kill'd the Prophets, and ſtoned them that were ſent; and when Chriſt the Son was come
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47505:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
who is Heir and Lord over all, they ſaid, <hi>We have a Law, and by our Law he ought to dye.</hi> Several more Inſtances might be given, how many went about to eſtabliſh Cruelty and Oppreſſion by a Law, as in the <hi>Ten Perſecutions,</hi> and in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s Dayes, who was called, <hi>A Chriſtian Princeſs,</hi> yet how many ſuffered <hi>Martyrdom</hi> by a Law in her Dayes, for their Teſtimony for God and the Truth, according unto what God had manifeſted unto them in their Day and Time; and if you go about to do the ſame Thing, and perſiſt in it, know ye, that the Lord God of Heaven and Earth, whoſe Power is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreſiſtible,</hi> when he riſeth to plead with Man for Sin, and whoſe Glory far excels the Sun in its Brighteſs; the ſame Way by which you think to <hi>exalt your ſelves,</hi> and <hi>Lord it over his Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi> will he aſſuredly bring you down, and cauſe you to bow before him, either to acknowledge his Power and Soveraignity over all, and that <hi>he alone ought to be worſhipped,</hi> as King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> did, and that <hi>in Truth and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs of Heart,</hi> or worſe, to wit, bring Deſtruction upon you, as he did upon <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt, who thought to bring <hi>Iſrael again into Bondage;</hi> and as he did <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> and his Sons, who thought to have the whole Stock of the <hi>Jews</hi> in the Provinces of King <hi>Ahaſuerus,</hi> deſtroyed; but the Lord wrought their Deliverance, and brought Deſtruction upon their Enemies: therefore <hi>in vain is it for Man to ſtrive againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker;</hi> for when did any ariſe up againſt God and his People, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper? Therefore be inſtructed, and take Counſel you <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in this Nation, and elſewhere, who oppoſe the Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God in his People, and would limit all according to your Way and Will, or otherwiſe they muſt ſuffer; be not overwiſe in your own Eyes, neither think it an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndervaluing</hi> unto you to take Counſel and Advice at ſo mean a People as we, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed People of the Lord called <hi>Quakers,</hi> are: For of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Truth, God in the Riches of his Love, in and through Chriſt Jeſus, our Lord and alone Saviour, hath appeared unto us, and manifeſted the Way of Life and Salvation in us, and unto us by his good Spirit, which he hath given unto us to profit withall; and many have been the <hi>Admonitions, Counſels</hi> and <hi>Advice</hi> of the Lord unto you, through and by his Servants; which ye too little have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, but rather made a Mock of them and what they have ſpoaken and written, accounting them as <hi>Mad Men,</hi> as they of old did the Servant of the Lord, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9.11. Nevertheleſs, as a Servant
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47505:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
of the Lord, and in Love and Good-will unto you, as one that really deſireth your Good &amp; the Good of all Men, my Adviſe and Counſel unto you is, to hearken and lend an Ear unto that <hi>Light</hi> in you, which ſecretly manifeſts Sin, and reproves for it; for of a certain Truth, that is a Meaſure of the Good Spirit of God, that will reprove you for your Cruelty &amp; Oppreſſion, and ſhew you <hi>you ſhould not do ſo againſt your Fellow-Servants; That</hi> will reprove you for your Pride and Haughtineſs of Spirit, and ſhew you <hi>what is Good, and what the Lord requires of you, that is, to do Juſtly, to love Mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God,</hi> Mic. 6.8. That will reprove you for Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Curſing, Vain and Idle Talking, Wantonneſs, Whoredom, Drunkenneſs, and all Manner of Uncleanneſs and Evil whatſoever, though done never ſo ſecretly, yet the Lord is privy to it, and his all-ſeeing Eye beholds all the <hi>Actions</hi> of the Sons and Daughters of Men, and by the Meaſure of his Good Spirit he ſtrives with them, and ſheweth them they ſhould not do the Thing that is Evil; and by the ſame calleth unto them for <hi>Amendment of Life;</hi> and thoſe that <hi>turn at the Lord's Reproof, he will pour forth his Spirit upon them, and make known his Words unto them;</hi> but if <hi>you ſ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t at nought the Counſel of the Lord, and will none of his Reproofs</hi> (as ſome of Old did, and too many now do) <hi>then will he laugh at your Calamity, and mock when your Fear cometh as Deſolation, and Deſtruction as a Whirl-wind; then you may call, and hee'l not anſwer, and ſeek him early, and not find him, becauſe you hated Knowledge, and did not chuſe</hi> (mark that) <hi>the Fear of the Lord which is to depart from Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore muſt you eat the Fruit of your own Way, and be fill'd with your own Devices that do ſo; <hi>But who hearkeneth unto the Lord, ſhall dwell ſafely, and be quiet from Fear of Evil,</hi> Prov. 1.25. and ſo on: Therefore be inſtructed ye <hi>Rulers</hi> of this Nation, and take Counſel of the Great Law-giver Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaid, <hi>As ye would that all Men ſhould do unto you, ſo do you unto them; for this is the Law and the Prophets;</hi> and remember the Parable that Chriſt ſpoak, <hi>A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain King which would take Account of his Servants, &amp; when he began to reckon, there was one brought before him that ow'd him ten Thouſand Talents, &amp; had nothing to pay withal; but his Servant humbled himſelf, &amp;c. and his Lord frankly forgave him the Debt; but he not doing ſo by his Fellow-Servant,</hi> what did befal him? And doth not Chriſt teach his to pray, <hi>Forgive us our Treſpaſſ<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, as we forgive them that treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs againſt us?</hi> Now if you cannot forgive them that treſpaſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47505:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
you, how can you expect to be forgiven of God? And if Men ought to forgive them that treſpaſs againſt them, then ſure, they ought not to perſecute ſuch as never treſpaſſed againſt them I would ask you one <hi>Queſtion;</hi> Wherein have we given Occaſion to be thus dealt with? what <hi>Plots</hi> or <hi>Evil Contrivances</hi> againſt the King or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment have we been found in ſince God raiſed us up to be a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? or what have you againſt us, except in the Matter of our God? Now if you ſhould ſay, <hi>We do not obey the Law,</hi> I then again query, What wholeſom Law is there that we diſobey? But if it be a Law that would limit in the Worſhip and Service of God, who alone in that Caſe is the Law-giver to his People, and ought to be ſubjected unto, then I query, What Power have you to make a Law to bind the Conſciences of God's People in the Worſhip of God more then Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and her Parliament had, by which ſo many <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were put to Death (which you condemn as Evil in t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em) for the Teſtimony of their Conſciences, according unto what God in their Day made manifeſt unto them; was not ſhe called a <hi>Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,</hi> and lawfully deſcended to the Crown, &amp;c? But if you ſay, <hi>They were perſecuted becauſe they bore Teſtimony to the Truth, but you becauſe you are in Error, &amp;c.</hi> How do you know that? could not the Miniſters of thoſe Laws ſay as much to the Sufferers as you do unto us? are you guided by an infallible Spirit in what you do? nay ſure, for the Spirit of God never led any to ſuch Things; but if any were in Error, they were to be reproved and admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and after the ſecond Admoniſhing rejected, not caſt into Priſon, or ſpoiled of their Goods, and the like. But it may be ſome may ſay <hi>They had not Power;</hi> Was not all Power in Heaven and Earth given unto Chriſt? and where did he give his Church (as you would be reckoned) Power to do ſo? And therefore you that are called <hi>Lord-Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Men,</hi> ought not you rather, if Men were in Error, to convince them by the Truth, and ſtop the Mouths of Gain-ſayers by ſound Doctrine, then to ſtir up <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> to make Laws to take honeſt Men and Womens Eſtates from them, impriſon and baniſh them for their Conſciences towards God, and becauſe they cannot put into your Mouthes; and alſo to preſs the Miniſters of thoſe Laws to put them into Execution? did ever <hi>Peter, John, Paul,</hi> or any of thoſe <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Goſpel-Miniſters</hi> do ſo? Is this like <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Goſpel Diſpenſation?</hi> Nay ſure, therefore away with it all, you that profeſs <hi>Chriſtianity</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:47505:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
of all Sorts, whether <hi>Papiſts, Epiſcopal Men, Presbyterian</hi> or what ſoever, and learn to <hi>do as you would be done by;</hi> and the ſame Liberty you would have your ſelves, the ſame give unto others in Exerciſes of Religion, they living Peaceable, not ſeeking the Subverſion of the Government, nor the Hurt of any; and this would heal the Nations Breaches, and make it as a Body or Family, as it ought to be, ſeeking the Good &amp; Preſervation one of another, both in Liberty and Eſtates, &amp;c. But this perſecuting, killing and deſtroying one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about Religion, never was of God, but ſprung from the Devil, the Father of all Cruelty and Perſecution; for Truth hurts none; he <hi>came not to deſtroy Mens Lives, but to ſave them.</hi> But it may be ſome may ſay, <hi>This is not Cruelty, but a Law that is for the Good of the Nation;</hi> ſo might all ſay that made Laws in ſuch Caſes; but I ſay, it is not any Law or Cuſtom of a Nation whatſoever that can juſtifie any Man before the Juſt and Equal God, in doing the Thing that is unjuſt, and whatever is contrary to Chriſt's Command (who ſaid, <hi>as ye would all Men ſhould do unto you, ſo do ye unto them</hi>) is unjuſt, and to be accounted for unto the great Law-giver Chriſt Jeſus: Therefore do not ſmooth and flatter your ſelves in ſaying, <hi>We have a Law (and the like)</hi> for the ſame did they ſay that are gone before you, who were found doing the ſame Things, and ſo juſtifie the Wicked, and condemn the Sufferings of the Righteous in all Ages; <hi>But he that juſtifieth the Wicked, and he that condemneth the Juſt, even they are both Abomination to the Lord,</hi> Prov. 17.15. It is your Good we deſire, and many Times it is in our Hearts bowed down before the Lord, both in Soul and Body, to pray unto him in your behalf, that he would change your Hearts, and cauſe you to be otherwiſe minded, that we might live a godly and quiet Life in all Honeſty as becometh the Goſpel: and if for theſe and ſuch like Things we ſuffer, the Good will of him that appeared in the Buſh (who had heard, and doth hear the Groans of his Peo<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, and was come down <hi>to deliver them</hi>) be done, who hitherto hath given us Strength and Patience to undergo what he hath ſuffered to be infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>upon us for his Name ſake,</hi> and our Hope and Truſt is, will do unto the End, as we abide faithful to him, to whom be <hi>Glory over all, forever,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>From One that really deſires the Proſperity of the Truth, and the Welfare of all Men, <hi>Alexander Lawrence</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
